Sadly, I've um seen all of those things
happen all too often in my career and
it's happened to me. I think black staff
still
face this constant barrage of being
undermined by their managers, including
in front of students, and students are
aware of that. You know, that I've had
students who are quite clear that they
are frightened to be too associated with
black staff, even black black students,
because of that feeling that we're all
illegitimate in the sector. And that
just undermines people. So, that comes
that when people already always feeling
that their work is not good enough,
being told directly and indirectly,
"Nothing about you is good enough.
You're here on sufferance." Then when
more things happen, they're already
depleted. And sometimes that leads to
people
literally being bullied out of their
jobs.
So, there have been kind of instances
that I've been privy to or experienced
myself in terms of harassment of black
members of staff. I think often there
isn't really a vehicle for them to
channel those
instances or those racialized instances.
And often when they have kind of
explained to senior members of staff or
management about those experiences, they
often haven't gone any further and
they've often been trivialized. So,
in a lot of cases, a lot of black
members of staff, when they're kind of
talking about these instances of
racialization,
it kind of doesn't go anywhere and it's
that whole fear of um
it's that whole fear of creating further
stigmatization or marginalization for
themselves. So, what you've found what
we found is because a lot of these
arguments aren't taken any further and
there's no gravitas towards kind of
penalizing racialized or racist
behavior, what we found is that a lot of
BAME academics, they often keep these
stories to themselves, often keep these
instances to themselves.
And the internal effect affects things
like well-being, mental health,
engagement professionally.
And that's against the backdrop of kind
of hyper-surveillance, kind of deficit
model approaches, racial
microaggressions, and those types of
things.
The way I've tried to address it is
obviously be as professional as
possible. So, I kind of spoken to
members of staff about, you know,
undermining, working as a collective,
how they are actually fulfilling that
kind of normative and deficit approach
of, you know, black and ethnic minority
academics. And I've kind of emphasized
them the importance of not peddling that
particular
viewpoint from students and from members
of staff. So, that's how I've dealt with
it. And how I've kind of spoken to
students about it is just to make them
aware that, you know, universities are
microcosm of society and they're diverse
in their space. And by proxy of that,
it's not unusual for you to have people
that may teach you that are from
different ethnic backgrounds. There's no
such thing as one particular dominant
ethnic background that should be in
higher education. And obviously
historically, it has been, you know,
middle-class white people. But it's
important that we try and challenge
students to dismantle that narrative,
that visual narrative as well.
And in doing that, kind of make them
open to different canons of knowledge
and different bodies of knowledge in
terms of what they learn and how they
learn. And that there's more than one
way to learn. And I think that's
important. So, it's a very different
approach that you take with students
than when you do with staff. Because
with students, I think in a lot of
cases, they're malleable. You can still
change, if they want to, you can change
their way of thinking. But with staff
that are, you know, slightly older than
the students, they should know better. A
lot of their approaches are fixed. And
sometimes, they can be conscious.
Sometimes, they can be unconscious. But
in terms of those kind of racist
instances and practices, they're still
insidious and they still happen in a way
that goes under the radar because I
think what we all gravitate towards are
the covert examples of racism and in
doing that I think we're we're not so
mindful of the more insidious kind of
covert forms of racism. Instead of So we
look for more of the overt examples and
what we need to look for are the covert
examples where our members of staff,
faculty of color being continuously
undermined.
So every time I meet a student who tells
me that they've experienced some kind of
racial harassment or xenophobia, the
first thing I tell them is
and I know a lot of people will say you
know confront it. The first thing I say
is your safety. Do you think at that
point at that given moment I do you feel
safe? If you don't feel safe, then just
walk out. But if you've got a critical
mass around you, confront it, you know,
just question that what is happening.
But the most important thing for us is
report. So I think you know, reporting
to your police, reporting to your local
counselor, reporting to the
to the university so that it's all
logged because until and unless there's
documentary evidence of that this is
happening on such a large scale, I don't
think we will, you know, be able to
effectuate change in the same way we
want to.